

contact

Somewhere in the UK

+44 nope:)

www.jmsalopes.com sa@jmsalopes.com



languages

portuguese & english fluency

programming

♥ Java, C/C++/C# Python, PHP & **JavaScript**

interests

professional: privacy, anonymization, crypto, vulnerability research, exploit dev, netsec, social engineering personal: music, hardware, motorcycles, gaming, reading

social skills

Dealing closely with clients I've learned to understand their requirements and manage their expectations.

- Junior Security Consultant

Working in an multi-purposed team I've hardened my teamwork skills and nurtured my leadership traits. - Junior Researcher

Researching a subject unacquainted by my colleagues, I enhanced my problem solving skills and autonomy. - Masters student

experience

2014-... **MWR InfoSecurity**

Manchester, United Kingdom

Junior Security Consultant

Mobile and web application penetration testing:

- iOS and Android application pentesting
- Device/build reviews
- Source code auditing

2012-2014 LASIGE Research Unit

Lisbon, Portugal

Junior Researcher

Researching privacy and anonymity in general, but namely:

- How to assure and enforce infosec properties in a smart-grid
- · Anonymous and distributed communication over the Internet

2012-2013 LASIGE Research Unit

Lisbon, Portugal

Masters student

Studied the design and use of forward error correction (FEC) codes, namely fountain codes, in malicious environments.

Detailed achievements:

- In-depth study of LT codes
 - Found an attack to break the code's resilience
- In-depth study of Raptor codes, in greater detail the RaptorQ code
 - First public implementation of IETF's RFC 6330 (the OpenRQ library)
 - Found an attack to break RaptorQ's resilience

projects

2015-... **Gobby**

https://gitorious.org/gobby

Co-developed an iOS chat application with different levels of vulnerabilities/protections. The aim of the application is to provide training in iOS application security assessment.

2014-... OpenRQ Library

http://www.lasige.di.fc.ul.pt/openrq

Lead developer/maintainer

Developer/maintainer

In the context of my Masters' thesis I implemented a RaptorQ library in Java. Since then, it has evolved into an open source project. It offers a simple but powerful API, so any developer can use it on his applications. It is suitable for high-performance network applications, but its flexible API allows for an easy integration with common network communication software.

2009-... XMakemol2 Project

https://github.com/zemasa/xmakemol2

Lead developer/maintainer

XMakemol is a mouse-based software for viewing atomic and other chemical systems. It reads XYZ input files and renders atoms bonds and hydrogen bonds. XMakemol2 was created from the original XMakemol software to fill in the need to manipulate/operate a XYZ file. Namely by adding/removing atoms and applying geometric transformations to atoms or molecules.

technical skills

IT skills

- Deep understanding of Linux
- Strong programming skills in Unix systems
- Familiarity with .NET technologies
- Experience with distributed systems technoloaies
- Experience with SOAP and RESTful web services
- Wealth of knowledge in forward error correction techniques and erasure coding
- Experience with RPC and Java RMI
- Experience with AJAX technologies
- Experience with Nagios and systems monitoring

InfoSec skills

- Deep understanding of popular network protocols, namely TCP, UDP, IP, SNMP and HTTP
- Strong knowledge of encryption algorithms and modes of operation
- Experience with IPsec and VPN technologies
- Basic reverse engineering skills
- Basic computer forensics skills
- Familiarity with 802.1X, BT and RFID security
- Experience with scanning, vulnerability analysis and penetration testing tools.
- iOS and Android OS and application security
- Source code review and auditing

education

2011–2013 MSc in Information Security (avg. 18/20) University of Lisbon, Faculty of Science

"Communication with RaptorQ Erasure Codes in Malicious Environments"

This thesis describes an attack to IETF's RFC 6330 which specifies the RaptorQ erasure code. Additionally, from this work resulted the first public implementation of

the RatorQ FEC code — the OpenRQ library. (final grade: 19/20)

2008–2011 Licentiate in Informatics Engineering (avg. 14/20) University of Minho

certifications & awards

2013 **Best Paper in Security of Computer Systems and Communications** INForum Conference Best paper in the SCSC track.

2015 Offensive Security Certified Professional Offensive Security

"OSCP challenges the students to prove they have a clear practical understanding of the penetration testing process and lifecycle through an arduous 24h certification exam."

publications

Stopping Rapid Tornadoes with a Puff

José Lopes, Nuno Neves IEEE Security & Privacy, 2014 Robustness of the RaptorQ FEC Code Under Malicious Attacks

José Lopes, Nuno Neves INForum. 2013